- Previously on Gotham...
- Shut up and die.
OSWALD: Say hello to Butch.
(grunts)
No!
(gunshot)
BRUCE: She's paralyzed
and has lost the will to live.
IVY: If Selina ingests
this, it'll find its way
- to her wound.
- SELINA: I'm better.
So now I have to find
the freak who shot me.
ECCO: Welcome to
the Church of Jeremiah.
Selina!
NYGMA: This time,
woke up on a rooftop.
No idea how I got there
or what happened during
the preceding hours.
Who the hell are you?
You don't remember?
What is happening to me?
Gonna need people I can
trust watching over this place.
- You could be my deputy
here in Haven.
- Thanks.
OSWALD: Well, if
it isn't my old friend
Mr. Penn.
You shouldn't have
come here, Oswald.
Perhaps you shouldn't
have stolen my people.
BARBARA: Hi, Pengy.
- OSWALD:
Jim!
- Barbara, no.
♪♪
(child crying)
(groaning)
(coughing)
(gasping)
(screaming)
(coughing)
(coughs)
(shuddering)
(muffled chatter)
(baby crying)
(woman crying)
GORDON: Over here!
- (coughs)
- Over here!
Over here!
This woman needs
medical attention.
Find a doctor. Go. Hey, hey!
You! Hey, listen up.
Pair up. I need teams
going in looking for survivors.
- Go. Get those people back!
- (siren wailing)
Hey. You.
Set up a triage over here.
Hey. Hey, come on. Snap to.
Focus. There's gonna
be a lot of wounded.
Look at me. Look at me.
All right. Find all the
medical supplies you can. Go.
You did this. You
brought the gangs here!
No! I would never allow that.
None of them had
explosives, that I know of.
BULLOCK: Jim!
We need to get
these fires out, Harvey.
We got nothing to put hoses on.
Use the drinking water. Do it.
Hey. Hey!
Get those hoses over here now!
(indistinct chatter,
siren wailing in distance)
Jim.
Harvey. Flames are dying.
We need more teams inside.
- There have to be survivors.
- I know.
It's just, an officer
just found this.
It's yours.
♪♪
GORDON: As of now,
the death toll stands at 311.
49 injured.
More than two dozen
unaccounted for.
WALKER: I'm so
terribly sorry, Captain.
Do you have any idea
who's responsible?
There was an incursion
by several of the gangs.
Any one of them
could've done it.
Right now, it's impossible
to rule anyone out.
I'm working on getting you help.
You've been promising
me help for weeks.
I have bodies lined
up in the streets.
You have every right
to be upset, Captain.
- But I'm doing
everything I can...
- Yeah.
To make sure
that you and your...
(shouting in distance)
Let them through.
- There he is!
- Let them through!
Let them through.
It's okay. It's all right.
MAN: When are you
gonna find out who did this?
My family was in there.
How do we know we're safe here?
GORDON: I know...
I know each one of you
lost someone you care for.
I share your grief.
I share your anger.
But whoever
destroyed that building
can't destroy the
hope we've built.
Not unless we let them.
I swear,
I promise I won't stop until
I find those responsible.
Justice will be done.
How are you gonna stop
it from happening again?
(crowd shouting)
It was a nice try.
Can you blame
them? They're angry.
It's gonna take more than words.
Someone has to
pay for this, soon.
Well, the department's not
exactly firing on all cylinders.
We got more men than bullets,
and we ain't got that many men.
Lucius, I need something.
Comb through every piece
of evidence you can find.
I need to know who
did this, and how.
It's not gonna be easy. The
size of the crime scene alone...
Do whatever you have
to do. The clock is ticking.
More than you know.
When Barbara and I showed
up, that's when the building blew.
She vanished right after.
This doesn't make
sense. Not even for her.
Nothing makes sense anymore.
You're in charge, Harvey.
BRUCE: Selina!
Oh.
Hey.
I was afraid you
didn't get my signal.
Lucius said the range
was only a couple miles.
Oh, you know me, Master Bruce,
I managed to muddle through.
So go on, then.
How did that happen?
I let my guard down.
You're telling me that
your captors shackle you,
they leave a radio transponder
in your pocket and...
and your weapons?
Really?
I think you're telling porkies.
It was Selina.
She's gone after
Jeremiah, alone.
You want to follow her, do you?
She's not herself, Alfred.
She's desperate for revenge.
She's gonna get
herself hurt, or killed.
Seems to be a little
bit of a recurring theme
with madam, isn't it?
You know, one of these
days you're gonna realize
you can't save her from herself.
Until that day comes...
I think we should go
and find her, don't you?
(gun clicks)
BARBARA: Let him in.
You're either here
for information,
or you somehow think I
might've had something to do
with that atrocity.
Penguin murdered Tabitha.
You knew he was at Haven.
You would've done
anything for revenge.
And I could've killed
him then and there.
So why didn't you?
Because the person who blew
up Haven has to be stopped.
That's all that matters now.
You're worried
Sirens could be next.
I've been putting out feelers.
Is that what that was?
He heard people
talking about a shady guy
lurking around
Haven before it blew.
This is Gotham.
You're gonna have to do
better than "shady guy."
How about a location?
A building in the northeast
corner of Harlow Park.
He says the guy's
holed up there.
How much is this gonna cost me?
Just do your job.
Get the bastard.
Did you really think I could've
murdered all those people?
I don't know.
I guess I deserve that.
BULLOCK (over radio): Jim.
Jim.
Jim, you read me?
Yeah.
We got a problem.
On my way.
(door opens, closes)
Oswald?
What are you doing here?
Jim, it has become
woefully apparent
that you are outmanned,
outgunned and out of options.
So I'm here to help.
That's generous of you.
(laughs): I'm just
getting started.
BULLOCK: Well.
Ain't you just Saint Nick
on a Christmas morning?
Don't be shy. Go.
Take all you can carry.
I'm guessing there
are strings attached?
No strings.
Save for the one
that we will cinch
around the neck of
the Haven bomber.
I lost people, too, Jim.
People you lured with
promises of safety and security,
only to have them incinerated.
But let's just hold that in
abeyance for the moment.
I would rather we put aside
our considerable differences,
and go get the
people some justice.
What do you say, partner?
(sighs)
Apparently,
I've been on a trip,
or I'm going on one.
I've also left myself a message.
"In A-T number 1215 knows."
In... nate?
In... grate? Inflate?
In... mate?
"Inmate number 1215 knows."
Inmate number 1215 knows!
Knows what?! (groans)
Okay. Okay, think.
Prison records. Where
do I get prison records?
(sighs)
Right.
♪♪
To hell with Penguin.
Haven wasn't your fault.
I told the people it was safe.
I made them into a target.
Jim, you gave 'em...
Don't tell me I gave
'em hope. They're dead.
All right, fan out.
We go building to
building, door to door.
Our source said this is
where we'll find the bomber.
He's here somewhere.
Alvarez, take a squad, grab
the north side of the street.
The rest of you,
cover the south.
To the vile miscreant
who murdered those
innocent Havenites,
you have nowhere to run!
There goes the
element of surprise.
OSWALD: We will root you out
like the vermin you are!
Two forces united
in one purpose!
(gunshot)
- Get back! Get back!
- Get down!
GORDON: Elevated
position, back to the sun.
(gun cocks)
BULLOCK: Looks like
we found our guy, huh?
(gunshot)
We're sitting ducks out here.
BULLOCK: And one Penguin.
Hey, Oswald, why
don't you crawl out there,
grab that bullhorn and tell
him to come down quietly?
(gunshot)
GORDON: Put your weapons down!
We have the building surrounded.
And we have more ammo than you!
Come out now with
your hands in the air.
MAN: Pretty cozy up here.
Thanks, guys.
I know that voice.
Zsasz?
Oh, hey, guys. What's up?
(gunshot)
(door creaks)
Oh.
It's impolite to
sneak up on people.
So is breaking and entering.
Heard you were dead, Ed.
Now what are you looking for?
I am given, and I am taken.
I was there from
your first breath,
and I will follow
you until your death.
(exhales) A name.
So...
you're looking for the name
of a prisoner at Blackgate.
Call it a personal matter.
- This folder's quite valuable.
- Right.
What is the going
rate on dust bunnies?
What I mean to say is,
this folder seems to be
quite valuable to you.
Well...
I'm guessing you
don't want money,
because, uh, it's worthless.
I don't tend to
carry snacks on me.
And if I had any bullets,
I would just shoot
you and take the folder.
So what is it that
you would like?
Your expertise.
Surely you've noticed
the giant plume of
smoke in the sky?
Someone blew up a building
we were using to house refugees.
We need to figure
out how they did it,
so we can prevent
them from doing it again.
So, the second smartest
man in Gotham...
needs my help.
Explosives are not my expertise.
Didn't realize you had one.
Hmm.
Just...
Why?
(exhales)
Do we have a deal or not?
Fine.
- (door opens)
- (sighs)
(gunshot)
I did not make that
building go boom, Jim.
Oh, please!
You gave up any
shred of honor long ago!
Why should we believe
a snake like you?!
Because I would never take
credit for somebody else's work.
Oh, no, you'd just betray
anyone and everyone
for the right price!
Is this about Sofia Falcone?
Because you should
really move past that.
It's not healthy.
(gunshot)
Oswald, concentrate.
Do you and your men
have enough ammo
to keep Zsasz pinned down
for a couple of minutes?
For you, Jim, let's
say... two and a half.
Concentrate all your fire
on that window up there.
Give me everything you
got, then abruptly cease fire.
You can count on me.
Spread the word.
MAN: All right,
guys, gather around,
we got new orders.
All right.
Ready?
Yeah.
Now!
Fire!
Keep it coming!
(slurping)
(watch beeping)
Cease fire!
Glad to see
you're still with us.
Thank you. Thank
you. You were great.
Glad there's no hard feelings.
Day's not over yet. Come on.
Well done, Jim.
We make a hell of a team.
That man is a menace.
Allow me to deal with him.
This is about more than just
your vendetta against Zsasz.
If he did this, I need to know
if it was a part of
something larger.
My point exactly.
One of the areas
in which I excel
is the loosening of tongues.
No. He's mine.
(siren wails)
♪♪
(people coughing)
SYKES: You're pushing
my men way too hard.
We're not gonna break through
for at least a couple more days.
There is absolutely no
way to make it on schedule.
(choking)
Well, not with that
attitude, you're not.
Now...
everyone...
let's reach inside and dig...
a little deeper, shall we?
'Cause that's the only way
you're all making
it out of this hole.
Come on. Put this on.
(muttering)
(giggling)
(continues giggling)
(clears throat)
Are these all the recruits?
Well, I thought you
would want quality
over quantity.
Not everybody can pass
a .38 caliber test of faith.
(gasps)
Yes...
you certainly have
set a very high bar
- for devotion.
- (gasps)
(sighs)
Oh. Almost forgot.
Bruce Wayne and
his sidekick Curls...
Or is he the sidekick? (giggles)
Anyway, they tried to infiltrate
our little operation here.
- Oh?
- Oh.
And Curls can walk, really well,
especially...
for a paraplegic.
Ah. And she wants to kill you.
A lot, FYI.
If I see her, I'll
give you a shout.
Oh... and kill her.
Mm.
Okay, recruits,
let's do like my daddy did
before my sixth
birthday and move out.
Ed?
The building's
superstructure is largely intact,
which would rule
out C-4 and Semtex.
Evidence of deflagration
would suggest something
with a slower burn
rate, like gunpowder
or nitroglycerin.
But for this level
of destruction,
that would require
a bomb that's...
20 cubic feet of
explosive material.
There's no way you could sneak
something that size into the building.
All the entrances were
guarded, which suggests maybe
that this was an inside job.
Or...
a classic locked-room mystery.
Man walks into a room, alone,
and is later found murdered.
There are no
windows, and one door,
which is locked from the inside.
The killer was already
inside the room.
So, the bomb was
already inside the building?
No.
The bomb was the building.
You don't need to
smuggle in explosives
when you can
detonate 250 gallons
of highly pressurized
heating oil
that's coursing
through all the floors.
True, but that
doesn't explain this.
Glass?
Presumably from there.
No, there's no way that that
would blast in
with that explosion.
That would make all of that
glass go out onto the street.
Unless whatever ignited
those heating oil tanks...
BOTH: Smashed
through that window.
Ow.
This is a really nice table.
We got a dozen
witnesses that saw you
walk out of that building
before it went kabooey.
Yeah. I heard some
gangs had taken over.
Figured, with you guys occupied,
I might help myself to
some of your supplies.
Hey, do you guys have
any canned peaches?
Man, I'd trade an arm
and a leg for that right now.
Not mine, somebody else's.
If you're innocent, why shoot up
a city block full of cops?
Because it was full of cops,
who were also
trying to shoot me.
And, guys, those were
warning shots. I mean,
if I really wanted
to kill you...
- you'd be dead.
- You got a pen?
I want to write this
guy a thank-you letter.
ZSASZ: Do the math.
If I blew up a
building full of people,
I would have covered
every inch of my body
in sweet, sweet scars.
You guys want to
do a strip search?
(door opens)
Got Lucius on the
horn for you, Cap.
Stay on him.
I'd let Alvarez do it.
He's handsome.
Lucius, talk to me.
LUCIUS: Haven wasn't
destroyed by a bomb.
It was an RPG, like the one
that took down the chopper.
You sure?
I'm holding what's left
of it in my hand right now.
We found pieces
of it in the rubble.
It was fired through
the basement window,
detonated the fuel oil tank.
And we're still trying
to figure out exactly
which rooftop it was fired from.
- Rooftop?
- LUCIUS: Yes.
The only angle you could
hit this tank from is above.
Our only suspect
was on the ground.
Zsasz was seen
leaving the building
moments before it blew.
Looks like you
need a new suspect.
Jim! (chuckles)
Ah. I know the wheels of justice
turn slowly, so
I'm here to provide
- a modicum of grease.
- Oswald,
you need to leave right now.
Still claiming he's
innocent, is he?
Yes. And as much
as I hate to admit it,
the evidence is backing him up.
What the hell's going on?
Harvey, according to Lucius,
- Zsasz couldn't have done it.
- (Oswald sighs)
I did not expect
you to go soft, Jim.
Actually, I did.
Which is why I didn't
come alone. (whistles)
- ♪♪
- (chuckles)
Bring me Victor Zsasz.
Torturing...
Torturing Zsasz into confessing
won't give the people justice.
As misguided as he is,
my old friend Jim is
correct in this instance.
Despite our enflamed passions,
we cannot rush to judgment.
- There will be a trial.
- MEN: Yeah!
And we will let
the people decide.
MEN: Yeah!
Good to know who's
really in charge here, Jim.
LUCIUS: This is
it, the exact place
where the RPG was fired.
Impressive.
Calculated the angle of incident
to follow the trajectory through
the window, into the fuel oil tanks.
Yep.
That, and the RPG
case is right over there.
So, now we know how it was done;
hopefully this holds
some clues as to who.
I should get this
back to the lab.
Doubtful that someone
who could pull off
such an intricate plot
would forget to wear gloves.
True, but it's all
I've got to go on.
Well, maybe I'm wrong.
I hope so.
I truly hope that you
find whoever did this...
and you make them pay.
As promised.
I appreciate your help, Ed.
Couldn't have
done it without you.
And if you tell anyone
I said that, I will deny it.
"Inmate number
1215. Frank McCann."
(quietly): Frank McCann.
Deceased? No!
No! No, you can't be dead!
(shouts) No!
(shouts)
Lucius! Hey!
Di... Did you see who
blew up this building?
Hey! (groans)
Deaf old bat.
Hopefully she's not blind, too.
(excited chatter)
(door opens)
MAN: There he is.
(chatter continues)
BULLOCK: I got
no love for Zsasz,
but are we really
gonna let this happen?
Look at them, Harvey.
If we try to stop it, they'll
turn that anger against us.
We've got to do something.
Yeah? Like what?
I make another speech?
Maybe this is what
the people need.
- (gavel bangs)
- Order in the court!
So, um, will I be
appointed a lawyer?
I feel like my rights
are being violated.
Not your right to
remain silent. Bailiff.
No, no, no, no, no...
And where exactly did
you see the defendant
minutes before the explosion?
Coming out of the building.
The very building that
mere moments later
was engulfed in
flames that would claim
so many beloved souls?
(crying)
(quiet chatter)
Are there any other witnesses
who can back up
this man's claim? Oh.
- Here.
- Yep. Here.
(chuckles weakly)
Captain Gordon would
have this court believe
that all of you fine
citizens are mistaken.
(crowd exclaiming)
He claims that Mr. Zsasz is
not responsible for the bombing.
(crowd exclaiming)
Captain Gordon, if you
would like to say something,
now is the time.
(overlapping chatter)
MAN: Tell us something.
♪♪
It wasn't a bomb.
(crowd exclaiming)
GORDON: It wasn't a bomb.
Shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh.
A rocket-propelled
grenade, fired from a rooftop.
If Zsasz was on the ground,
as your witnesses claim,
he couldn't have done it.
I know you all want justice.
So do I.
You're angry.
You're scared.
For months now, you've
been hearing me say
help is coming.
Truth is, we may be on our own.
And if that's true,
what we do now is
more important than ever.
This...
This is not justice.
It's not who we are.
I'll consider that
your closing argument.
Now that the defense has
rested, let's put it to the crowd.
What say you, jury?
CROWD: Guilty!
(overlapping shouting)
(chanting): Guilty!
Guilty! Guilty!
(chanting continues)
(cheering, shouting)
(gavel banging)
By the power vested in me
by... well, me,
I sentence you, Victor Zsasz,
to die.
Any last words?
(muffled mumbling)
Well said.
- (people screaming)
- Get him out of there.
Overruled!
What the hell are you doing?!
Trying to keep you all from
making a terrible mistake.
OSWALD: See?
Jim Gordon cares more
about protecting a murderer
than he does about
protecting you!
You've lost them, Jim.
They don't believe
in you anymore.
They're mine now.
BULLOCK: I got
to be honest, Jim,
I don't know how safe
Zsasz will be at the GCPD.
There's more than a few cops
that want to see him on a slab.
GORDON: That's why
we're not taking him there.
Wait. Tell me this is
not a catch and release.
What choice do I
have? Either I let him go,
or he's dead for
something he didn't do.
Thank you, Jim.
I'm not doing this for you.
Of course not.
This city will never be
what you want it to be, Jim.
It's always gonna belong
to the bad guys, like me.
Give him your gun, Harvey.
What?
Yeah. What?
Give him your gun.
Jim.
- Do it!
- ZSASZ: You got a
death wish, Jim?
'Cause I'll kill you.
Harvey, too.
Maybe.
Maybe I'm just tired of
listening to you, Victor.
Do it.
You know what? You seem tired.
Maybe we should do this
another day, yeah?
People like you are
always trying to own this city.
But you never will.
Now get the hell out of my face.
See you around, Jim.
A shoot-out?
- Are you serious?
- What? I could've taken him.
That's not the point. Never...
ever ask me to do
anything like that again.
Pull yourself together.
(grunting, screaming)
You see, a river cuts through
rock not because of its power,
but because of its persistence.
So what do we do when
we feel like giving up?
WORKERS: Dig a little deeper.
And what do we do when we
can't possibly go on any longer?
WORKERS: Dig a little deeper.
And what do we...
SELINA: Deep enough?
(gasping)
(grunting)
(straining): Well, Selina,
I must say...
(gasps)
Don't say anything.
- (shouts)
- BRUCE: Selina!
- Selina!
- Let me go!
BRUCE: It's done! It's over.
MAN (distant): Jeremiah!
We need to get out of here, now.
(people shouting, coughing)
(Nygma panting)
I hate stairs.
Oh, God.
(wheels squeaking)
(gasps) Oh, no! Go away!
No... hey, wait. I need
to know what you know.
Oh, please. Oh, oh,
please don't hurt me.
Listen, lady, I'm
not gonna hurt you.
I just want to
know what you saw.
Uh, uh, the-the roof.
You, you were on the roof.
And you had some kind of a, uh,
you had some kind
of a, of a rocket.
Mm.
That's, that's not possible.
Uh, and-and you shot
it at-at-at that building.
Oh!
♪♪
(rapid beeping)
(panting)
Oh!
Oh, I'm sorry.
I promise,
I won't tell anybody.
I know you won't.
You said you wouldn't hurt me.
I'm really very sorry.
Oh, no! Oh, no! (screaming)
(car alarm blaring)
(siren wailing in distance)
BARBARA: Spotlight's off.
You forget to pay
the electric bill?
What do you want, Barbara?
Same as you.
To protect my people.
Your tip didn't pan out.
Well, I've got another one.
A lead on a guy selling RPGs.
He moves about, but...
That all?
I heard some of your
people went over to Penguin.
Yeah.
Well, you can't win them all.
Poor Jim.
All alone again.
Get out of here, Barbara.
No one knows what
it's like to be him.
To carry the weight.
I told you to leave.
I heard you.